Finding Aid for Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project publications 1949-ongoing
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project publications 1949-[ongoing] 1949-1961
Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project.
University of Michigan based project founded as a memorial to university students, faculty and staff who died in World War II and dedicated to the study of peacetime applications of atomic energy. Includes miscellaneous pamphlets, annual reports, brochures, bulletins, manuals, newsletters, proceedings, proposals, and reports relating to the project and its sponsored research.
0231 Bimu C530 2
1.3 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Printed material arrives periodically from the Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project (Donor No. 5276 ).
The publications are open for research.
In 1947, a War Memorial Committee appointed by the Regents of the university and chaired by Dean of Students, Erich A. Walter, launched a mission to gather ideas and suggestions from prominent individuals around the world for a living memorial to the 583 students and faculty who lost their lives in World War II. On May 1, 1948, the Regents approved the recommendation of the committee for a research center that would become a "comprehensive, non-classified, university-wide program of study of the peaceful applications and implications of atomic energy, as it affects society, education, industry, technology, and the whole body of scientific knowledge." (Box 4, Background Material, "The Phoenix Associates of the University of Michigan.") The program was given a name that evoked powerful symbols of hope and new life arising from the ashes of war. Within ten years, the Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project was foremost among educational institutions of the world in exploring and developing peaceful uses of the atom.
The official beginning of a "chain reaction" appeal to Michigan alumni to raise funds for the research center was on October 2, 1950. Signaling the opening was a full day and evening of meetings and rallies held in cities and towns around the world "linked by telephone broadcast." "Using the Atom to Strengthen America" was the theme of this first Atom Day. Atom Day subsequently became an annual tradition and a vehicle for bringing together prominent speakers and dignitaries to report to the public and industry on activities of the program.
The original fund-raising campaign was highly structured, well organized, and infused from the start with the energy and the commitment of a broad base of Michigan alumni nationwide. Fourteen national regional committees were established with Chester H. Lang at the head as National Executive Chairman and university president Alexander Ruthven actively participating. In the first ten years, 30,000 individuals and 350 commercial firms contributed a total of $8 million to support the project. Also in its first decade, the project sponsored 185 research investigations by faculty members in fifteen of the university's seventeen schools and colleges. From these studies, more than 400 technical publications were published. A key factor in the success of the project was the broad participation encouraged across campus, an aspect promoted and maintained from the start under the leadership of physicist and dean of the Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies, Ralph A. Sawyer, the first director of the project.
As early as 1951, substantial research was under way in the study of food preservation, the preservation of metal surfaces, and age determination of pre-historic organic materials. It wasn't long before the Phoenix Project began to play an exemplary role at the university in atomic law, atomic medicine, and radiochemistry. In 1952, the Survey Research Center began a study on the impact of atomic energy on the American public, the law school began a broad investigation of the legal implications of the Atomic Energy Act, and a memorial fund for cancer research was created in honor of Alice Crocker Lloyd, former dean of women. In subsequent years, investigations expanded to scores of disciplines ranging from anthropology to zoology.
A 1952 annual report noted that financial goals were reached and surpassed and that construction on a building would begin the following year. It would house facilities for safe handling and storage of high-level radiation sources containing laboratories for work in radiochemistry, engineering, botany, the health sciences, physics, and other fields. In 1955 bids were opened for a nuclear reactor to be built in a special unit at the north end of the Phoenix Laboratory funded through a $1 million Ford Motor Company donation. The reactor, the first ever requested for construction by an agency other than the Atomic Energy Commission (AEC) and one of the most powerful sources of nuclear fission outside the facilities of AEC, was dedicated on Atom Day in 1956. By 1957, the program included seven laboratories for atomic research built or equipped with Phoenix funds: Phoenix Memorial Laboratory, Ford Nuclear Reactor, Alice Crocker Lloyd Radiation Center, Alice Lloyd Memorial Center, Phoenix Radioisotope Laboratory, Plant Nutrition Laboratory, and Radiocarbon Dating Laboratory.
In 1957, the Regents provided authorization for seeking $2 million in undesignated funds to be used for continuation of what had become the largest academic teaching and training program in the world in the field of nuclear research. Equipment and research had usurped most of the original $8 million, and discussions were inaugurated for a second campaign, geared toward implementing a five-year plan, this time in collaboration with the Development Council. (One of the early derivatives of the Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project campaign was the establishment of an ongoing fund-raising organization for the university. Early in 1951, the project's National Executive Committee submitted a resolution to the Board of Regents recommending such a unit, and in May of 1952, the Development Council was formally organized. Campaign efforts were thereafter designed collaboratively.)
The project garnered national and international attention as funds supporting research led to fundamental scientific discoveries, most notably Donald Glaser's development of the liquid bubble chamber, which makes possible rapid, easily interpreted photographs of rare atomic interactions. Dr. Glaser, who received the Nobel Prize in 1960, conducted his original research under the auspices and with the financial support of the Phoenix Project after other agencies had rejected his idea. Glaser, by then professor of physics at the University of California, returned to Ann Arbor in 1961 to give the first Phoenix-sponsored Dewey F. Fagerburg Memorial Lecture, a venue designed to feature distinguished contributors in the nuclear energy field. The following year, Dr. Robert Oppenheimer was invited to the podium, speaking before one of the largest audiences ever in attendance at Rackham Lecture Hall.
Over the years, the laboratories were visited by hundreds of scientists, individuals, and government officials. In 1955, University of Michigan scientists participated considerably at the International Conference on Peaceful Uses of Atomic Energy in Geneva. Worldwide interest in these issues led to the founding of the International Cooperation Administration (ICA), an arm of the AEC. Under a contract with ICA, Phoenix became the primary consulting agency for providing expert advice to foreign countries initiating atomic energy programs.
From the mid-1960s, the Phoenix Project and its associated facilities were overseen by a director reporting to the university's vice president for research and an executive committee composed of faculty members from across campus. Faculty executive committee responsibilities included budgeting and long-term planning. The committee was charged with relating the work of Phoenix to the university's instruction and research programs. By 1996, the number of research projects funded and completed had reached 816. However, the actual share of university users of the reactor had dwindled to about twenty-five percent, with industry and government accounting for the rest. At the same time, since the early 1980s the budget to run the Ford Reactor came primarily from the university itself with little support from the government or the AEC.
In the late 1990s, with federal funding for nonmilitary nuclear research at low ebb, universities across the country began to shut down their reactors. In December 2000, University of Michigan Regents announced that because the operation continued to drain over $1 million a year from the university budget, formal processes were under way to decommission the reactor. Former university president James J. Duderstadt (who himself was attracted to the university's engineering school because of the Phoenix Project and was at the time of the announcement a key advisor to the secretary of energy and chair of the Nuclear Energy Research Advisory Committee) began with a host of other scientists, to lobby for federal funds to keep academic reactors running.
Although the Ford Reactor, a cornerstone of the Phoenix Project, was officially decommissioned in 2003, the Project itself was continued with a new purpose. In 2004, the Phoenix Project was given new life as the Michigan Memorial Phoenix Energy Institute, and was charged with spearheading the University's efforts in interdisciplinary energy research, policy, and education. In their vote to broaden the Phoenix Project's charter beyond atomic energy, the University's Board of Regents expanded the Project's scope to encompass all forms of energy, and ensured the continued legacy of the Phoenix Project by noting that the Energy Institute would promote "research on the development of energy policies that will promote world peace, the responsible use of the environment, and economic prosperity."
Directors of the Phoenix Center
1951-1959 Dr. Ralph A. Sawyer
1959-1961 Henry J. Gomberg
1961-1989 William Kerr
1989-1998 Ronald F. Fleming
1998-2001 John C. Lee (Interim Director)
2001-2003 David Wehe
The Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project Publications are divided into two series: Unit Publications and Topical Publications. The bulk of the publications document the early history of the Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project from 1949 to 1961.
Unit Publications contain printed material published specifically by the Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project. These publications are defined as being widely distributed and may be published at regular intervals. They are arranged by genre of publication. Topical Publications include printed materials published to document specific events or activities such as fund-raising or development or one-time conferences hosted by the Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project.
Subjects:
Nuclear energy--Study and teaching.; Nuclear energy--Research--History.; Nuclear energy--Research--Laboratories--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre/Form:
Bulletins.; Manuals.; Newsletters.; Proceedings.; Reports.; Proposals.
- Unit Publications
  The Unit Publications series (1 linear foot) includes annual reports under the title Progress Report for the period from 1951 to 1959. Researchers should consult the President's Report (call number FImu B3a) for Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project annual reports included in the annually compiled volumes covering the period from 1960 to 1983/84. The President's Report ceased publication after 1983/84. In 1986/87 and 1987/88 the Annual Report of Educational and Research Activities was published.
  The bulletins Michigan, the Atom, and Peace, published in 1949, and Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project, issued in 1961, describe the mission of the project. There is an incomplete run (six issues) of the bulletin The Phoenix covering the period 1961 to 1965. There are several manuals describing the operation of the Ford Nuclear Reactor. These include Operating a Research Reactor, printed in 1958, Ford Nuclear Reactor: Description and Operation published in 1962, and Organization and Rules of Practice of the Safety Review Committee and the Ford Nuclear Reactor issued in 1975.
  Newsletters include the News Bulletin, volumes 1 through 3 and 5, published from 1949 to 1951. The University of Michigan Nuclear Reactor Laboratory Quarterly Review published from 1988 through 1990 became Quarterly Review in 1991. The Bentley Library holds this title through 1995.
  Atom Day was an annual conference to discuss the research done at the Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project. At the fifth Atom Day on June 9, 1955, the Mason Memorial Library was dedicated. The Ford Nuclear Reactor was dedicated at the sixth Atom Day on November 16, 1956. The proceedings of these two conferences not only describe the research activities of the Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project but also include the dedicatory remarks.
  The Unit Publications series also includes proposals to General Motors and the Chrysler Corporation appealing for funds. The 1950 proposal to General Motors requests money for the budding atomic research programs proposed by members of the University of Michigan faculty. In 1959 the Proposal for the Chrysler Corporation sought funding for future research projects and described the Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project facilities, policies and procedures, and the atomic research conducted at the University of Michigan for the previous nine years. The two proposals issued in 1960 were developed to create a laboratory for thermonuclear fusion instruction and to design a research program in the social sciences to examine the social consequences of nuclear science.
  The reports document the research of the staff of the Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project such as resonance radiation as well as the importance of the peaceful study of the atom.
  - Annual Reports (Box 1)
    - Annual Report of Educational and Research Activities
      - 1986-1987 (Box 1)
      - 1987-1988 (Box 1)
    - Progress Report
      - 1951-1955 (Box 1)
      - 1956-1959 (Box 1)
  - Articles about the Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project
    - 1955, 1958, undated (Box 1)
  - Brochures
    - General undated (Box 1)
    - Radiation Services, undated (Box 1)
    - Tour of the Phoenix Memorial Laboratory and Ford Nuclear Reactor, undated (Box 1)
  - Budgets
    - Expenditures and Sources of Support, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Bulletins
    - The Phoenix vol. 1-2, 1961-1965 (Box 1)
    - Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project vol. 1, no.2, 1961 (Box 1)
    - Michigan, the Atom, and Peace, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Manuals
    - Ford Nuclear Reactor: Description and Operation, 1962 (Box 1)
    - Operating a Research Reactor, [1958] (Box 1)
    - Organization and Rules of Practice of the Safety Review Committee and the Ford Nuclear Reactor, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Newsletters
    - News Bulletin
      - Vol. 1-3 1949-1951, 3 folders (Box 1)
      - Vol. 5 1951 (Box 1)
    - The University of Michigan Nuclear Reactor Laboratory Quarterly Review
      - 1988-1990, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Quarterly Review
      - 1991-1995, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Posters
    - Dewey F. Fagerburg Memorial Lecture, 1962 (Box 1)
    - It Had to Happen in a Country Like This, undated (Box 1)
  - Press Releases
    - 1959-1960 (Box 1)
  - Proceedings
    - Atom Day
      - Fifth Annual Atom Day and Dedications of the Mason Memorial Library and the Phoenix Memorial Laboratory, June 9, 1955, 1955 (Box 1)
      - Sixth Annual Atom Day and Dedication of the Ford Nuclear Reactor, June 16, 1956, 1957 (Box 1)
    - Atom Reports Conference
      - 1953-1954, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Programs
    - 1961 (Box 1)
  - Proposals
    - Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project: A Special Presentation to the General Motors Corporation, circa 1950 (Box 1)
    - A Proposal for Establishing an Instructional Laboratory in Thermonuclear Fusion at the University of Michigan, 1960 (Box 1)
    - Proposal for the Chrysler Corporation, 1959 (Box 1)
    - A Proposal for the Establishment of a Research Program in the Social Sciences to Investigate the Social Consequences of Technological Change, with Special Reference to Nuclear Science, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Reports
    - High Resolution Detection of Radiation by Henry J. Gomberg et al
      - 1953 (Box 2)
      - 1954 (Box 2)
      - Final Report, 1959 (Box 2)
    - High-Resolution System of Autoradiography by Henry J. Gomberg, 1951 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project: The Aims and Purposes of the Atomic Research Program at the University of Michigan, [ca. 1952] (Box 2)
    - The Phoenix Project: A Continuing Investigation Into Peacetime Implications and Applications of Atomic Energy, circa 1959 (Box 2)
    - A Report to the Board of Regents on the Nuclear Research Reactor at the University of Michigan: A Description of the Facility, and Evaluation of the Hazards of Operation, and Provisions for Limiting These Hazards, 1953 (Box 2)
    - Resonance in Radiation
      - Resonance Radiation Effects of Low Energy Monochromatic X-Rays on Catalase, Report No. 2, by Ardath H. Emmons, 1959 (Box 2)
      - A Study of the Free Radical Yield Produced in 1-Bromobutane by Irradiation with Monochromatic X-Rays of Differing Photon Energies, Report No. 4, by William R. Clendenning, 1960 (Box 2)
    - Resonance in Radiation Effects
      - Technical Report No. 1, February 1960 (Box 2)
      - Technical Report No. 5, November 1960 (Box 2)
- Topical Publications
  The Topical Publications series (.3 linear foot) features conference abstracts of the fifth Symposium on X- and Gamma Ray Sources and Applications which was held at the University of Michigan in 1981. There are also several development brochures dating from 1949 to 1955 documenting various fundraising techniques.
  - Conferences (Box 2)
    - Fifth Symposium on X-and Gamma Ray Sources and Applications
      - Abstracts
        - Abstracts of Papers to be Presented at the Fifth Symposium on X-and Gamma Ray Sources and Applications, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Development
    - Brochures
      - Ann Arbor Donors to Phoenix, undated (Box 2)
      - Citation List, 1950 (Box 2)
      - Donor Roll of Honor, 1950 (Box 2)
      - Fundraising 1949-1955, undated (Box 2)
      - Givers, 1950-1951 (Box 2)
      - Honor Roll (Donors List), undated (Box 2)
      - The Race Is On, undated (Box 2)
    - Handbooks
      - Handbook for Special Gift Committee Members, circa 1950 (Box 2)
Related Material
The archival records of the Phoenix Project are described separately in the record group Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project records, 1947-ongoing